<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-10-15T02:37:13+00:00</updated><id>https://rodolfor-s.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Base space</title><subtitle>I am a Postdoctoral Fellow at the Institute for Quantum Computing, University of Waterloo. </subtitle><author><name>Rodolfo R. Soldati</name></author><entry><title type="html">Quantum Information in L∃∀N!</title><link href="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2025/quantum-information-in-lean/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quantum Information in L∃∀N!"/><published>2025-10-15T01:54:15+00:00</published><updated>2025-10-15T01:54:15+00:00</updated><id>https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2025/quantum-information-in-lean</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2025/quantum-information-in-lean/"><![CDATA[<p>I have joined forces with <a href="https://ohaithe.re/">Alex Meiburg</a> and <a href="https://scholar.google.com/citations?user=1jxgRYcAAAAJ&amp;hl=en">Léo Lessa</a>, to kickstart a formalization project for quantum information in the L∃∀N Interactive Theorem Prover! We have just announced a preprint telling the story of how we formalized the <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2510.08672"><em>Generalized Quantum Stein’s Lemma</em>!</a></p> <p>We chose this project for two reasons: First, because it was extensive and non-trivial enough to force us to build a robust body of quantum information that would allow for <em>other</em>, subsequent projects. The second reason is its interesting recent history. In 2010, Fernando Brandão and Martin Plenio proved the first theorem coined the Generalized Quantum Stein’s Lemma. A few years ago, in 2023, however, it was announced that the original proof had a problem, and couldn’t exactly be fixed. After some tries, there are two pieces of work, by <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.06410">Ludovico Lami</a> and <a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/2408.02722">Hayashi &amp; Yamasaki</a>, with a corrected proof. We chose to formalize H&amp;Y, for technical reasons, and it worked! See our paper to learn what we learned!</p> <p>I got to know Lean and the world of proof verification around 2023 during my PhD. I wanted to learn how to use Lean to improve my mathematics toolkit, and to see what would make sense to formalise in physics. Quantum information is a rather proof-based, and mathematically rigorous side of physics (now very much interdisciplinary as well), and so seems to be one of the best places to start this.</p> <p>In fact, <a href="https://lean-lang.org/use-cases/mathlib/">mathlib</a>, an ongoing library project for all of mathematics, formalised in Lean, contains a little bit of information theory, and even a version of Bell’s theorem! We are pushing further for quantum information more broadly, though, in the repository started by Alex: <a href="https://github.com/Timeroot/Lean-QuantumInfo">Timeroot/Lean-QuantumInfo</a>. Prove your favourite theorem and give us a pull request!</p>]]></content><author><name>Rodolfo R. Soldati</name></author><category term="postdoc,"/><category term="iqc,"/><category term="perimeter,"/><category term="lean,"/><category term="quantum,"/><category term="information"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I have joined forces with Alex Meiburg and Léo Lessa, to kickstart a formalization project for quantum information in the L∃∀N Interactive Theorem Prover! We have just announced a preprint telling the story of how we formalized the Generalized Quantum Stein’s Lemma!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dedicated to the memory of Ray Laflamme: responsible innovation in quantum technologies</title><link href="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2025/responsible-innovation-in-quantum-tech/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dedicated to the memory of Ray Laflamme: responsible innovation in quantum technologies"/><published>2025-07-11T02:16:44+00:00</published><updated>2025-07-11T02:16:44+00:00</updated><id>https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2025/responsible-innovation-in-quantum-tech</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2025/responsible-innovation-in-quantum-tech/"><![CDATA[<p>I am happy to share my participation in an invited review of the Physics in Canada journal, alongside my coauthors Bruna S. de Mendonça, Ria Chakraborty, Katya Driscoll, and Ray Laflamme: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2507.05192">Responsible Innovation in quantum technologies</a>. This, however, comes at very sad times, given the <a href="https://obituaries.therecord.com/obituary/raymond-laflamme-1092952717">news of Ray’s passing on the 19th of June</a>.</p> <p>Ray was a titan of scientific research, having shaped the landscape of quantum computing and information in Canada and the world. It is then incredibly inspiring to have been part of his group, and to have participated in this work concerning the push for responsible and ethical innovation in the field of quantum emergent technologies.</p>]]></content><author><name>Rodolfo R. Soldati</name></author><category term="ri,"/><category term="responsible,"/><category term="innovation,"/><category term="quantum"/><category term="technologies,"/><category term="rqt"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I am happy to share my participation in an invited review of the Physics in Canada journal, alongside my coauthors Bruna S. de Mendonça, Ria Chakraborty, Katya Driscoll, and Ray Laflamme: Responsible Innovation in quantum technologies. This, however, comes at very sad times, given the news of Ray’s passing on the 19th of June.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">QBronze148: O primeiro evento do QBrasil</title><link href="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2024/primeiro-evento-do-qbrasil/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="QBronze148: O primeiro evento do QBrasil"/><published>2024-11-24T20:44:03+00:00</published><updated>2024-11-24T20:44:03+00:00</updated><id>https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2024/primeiro-evento-do-qbrasil</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2024/primeiro-evento-do-qbrasil/"><![CDATA[<p>Para os lusófonos: eu e alguns colegas lançamos o QBrasil com o evento <a href="https://qworld.net/qbronze148/" target="_blank">QBronze148 (link abre em nova aba)</a>, uma organização sem fins lucrativos para ajudar a fomentar e disseminar conhecimento em tecnologias quânticas no país. O QBrasil é o braço tupiniquim do QWorld, organização internacional com os mesmos objetivos.</p> <p>Esse evento é o primeiro de muitos do tipo, e um requerimento do QWorld, que abre a colaboração entre essas partes (é chamado de <em>Entangling Workshop</em>). Portanto, é em grande parte um evento em inglês (apesar de que teremos muitos elemento em português). Um dos nossos principais objetivos no futuro é gerenciar e propagar conteúdo primariamente em português.</p>]]></content><author><name>Rodolfo R. Soldati</name></author><category term="qbrasil,"/><category term="qworld,"/><category term="quantum-computing,"/><category term="brasil"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Para os lusófonos: eu e alguns colegas lançamos o QBrasil com o evento QBronze148 (link abre em nova aba), uma organização sem fins lucrativos para ajudar a fomentar e disseminar conhecimento em tecnologias quânticas no país. O QBrasil é o braço tupiniquim do QWorld, organização internacional com os mesmos objetivos.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Visit to the Institute for Quantum Computing, Waterloo</title><link href="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2023/visit-to-iqc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Visit to the Institute for Quantum Computing, Waterloo"/><published>2023-01-13T22:45:05+00:00</published><updated>2023-01-13T22:45:05+00:00</updated><id>https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2023/visit-to-iqc</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2023/visit-to-iqc/"><![CDATA[<p>I am on a one-month research visit in Canada, at the IQC in Waterloo, from the 15th of January. I will take up research in the group of Prof. Raymond Laflamme.<br/> This visit is my first time in North America, and I look forward to the time spent there and the people I will meet. I am expecting some enjoyable and productive times!</p>]]></content><author><name>Rodolfo R. Soldati</name></author><category term="phd"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I am on a one-month research visit in Canada, at the IQC in Waterloo, from the 15th of January. I will take up research in the group of Prof. Raymond Laflamme. This visit is my first time in North America, and I look forward to the time spent there and the people I will meet. I am expecting some enjoyable and productive times!]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One person’s ancilla is another person’s target</title><link href="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2022/minimal-hbac-published/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One person’s ancilla is another person’s target"/><published>2022-07-12T09:26:20+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-12T09:26:20+00:00</updated><id>https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2022/minimal-hbac-published</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2022/minimal-hbac-published/"><![CDATA[<p>My latest preprint is finally out for everyone to read! In this work we improve on models of Heat-Bath Algorithmic Cooling (HBAC) protocols taking place in a NV centre in diamond. Find it at <a href="https://doi.org/10.1103/PhysRevLett.129.030601">Physical Review Letters.</a></p> <p>We use the model to analyse data extracted from an experiment that reaches the cooling limits of the protocol. In the experimental realization the reset qubits thermalize to two slightly distinct temperatures, which is in contrast to the previously known results determining the cooling limits, that depended on having a single heat bath. By solving the model analytically we are thus able to extend our knowledge of the lowest temperatures achievable to a system with two heat baths.</p> <p>Our model is capable of better accounting the experimental intricacies of implementing HBAC in a lab, in a minimal way: our refinements do not involve coherences, and we identify separate ways to control the convergence rate towards the steady state and to control the asymptotic temperature values.</p>]]></content><author><name>Rodolfo R. Soldati</name></author><category term="phd"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My latest preprint is finally out for everyone to read! In this work we improve on models of Heat-Bath Algorithmic Cooling (HBAC) protocols taking place in a NV centre in diamond. Find it at Physical Review Letters.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A minimal thermodynamics manuscript</title><link href="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2021/a-minimal-thermodynamics-manuscript/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A minimal thermodynamics manuscript"/><published>2021-09-30T20:47:23+00:00</published><updated>2021-09-30T20:47:23+00:00</updated><id>https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2021/a-minimal-thermodynamics-manuscript</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2021/a-minimal-thermodynamics-manuscript/"><![CDATA[<p>In a new branch of my PhD project, we study the thermodynamics of a reset implementation of algorithmic cooling. This is a device purifying the states of qubits, which initializes them for use in quantum computations. In the point of view employed, the purified state of the qubit is equivalent to a cooled state, in an interesting interplay between quantum thermodynamics and quantum information theory. Check it out in <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2109.14056">arXiv!</a><br/> For this study we collaborated with the groups at the University of Stuttgart. In a partnership with the experimental group at the institute, led by Prof. Wrachtrup and Dr. Durga Dasari, we applied our analysis to their NV-center set-up, allowing for a practical comparison of the algorithm with the theoretical bounds for the usual thermodynamic refrigerator, and further making available a set of results that may be used to investigate other experimental platforms.</p>]]></content><author><name>Rodolfo R. Soldati</name></author><category term="phd"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In a new branch of my PhD project, we study the thermodynamics of a reset implementation of algorithmic cooling. This is a device purifying the states of qubits, which initializes them for use in quantum computations. In the point of view employed, the purified state of the qubit is equivalent to a cooled state, in an interesting interplay between quantum thermodynamics and quantum information theory. Check it out in arXiv! For this study we collaborated with the groups at the University of Stuttgart. In a partnership with the experimental group at the institute, led by Prof. Wrachtrup and Dr. Durga Dasari, we applied our analysis to their NV-center set-up, allowing for a practical comparison of the algorithm with the theoretical bounds for the usual thermodynamic refrigerator, and further making available a set of results that may be used to investigate other experimental platforms.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Yet another preprint!</title><link href="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2021/yet-another-preprint/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Yet another preprint!"/><published>2021-06-15T15:25:23+00:00</published><updated>2021-06-15T15:25:23+00:00</updated><id>https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2021/yet-another-preprint</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2021/yet-another-preprint/"><![CDATA[<p>I’m very happy to announce the release of yet another preprint, this time one that has been on the works since I was a Master’s student.<br/> This is a topic very dear to me (it really makes me curious!), here it is: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2106.06803">Universal terms of the entanglement entropy in a static closed universe</a>.<br/> I have started these studies more or less four years ago at the Federal University of Minas Gerais with my then supervisor, Prof. Nelson Yokomizo, and with the help of our colleague Lucas Menicucci we are now ready to put this work out there.</p>]]></content><author><name>Rodolfo R. Soldati</name></author><category term="phd"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’m very happy to announce the release of yet another preprint, this time one that has been on the works since I was a Master’s student. This is a topic very dear to me (it really makes me curious!), here it is: Universal terms of the entanglement entropy in a static closed universe. I have started these studies more or less four years ago at the Federal University of Minas Gerais with my then supervisor, Prof. Nelson Yokomizo, and with the help of our colleague Lucas Menicucci we are now ready to put this work out there.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New preprint in town</title><link href="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2021/new-preprint-in-town/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New preprint in town"/><published>2021-05-20T08:22:16+00:00</published><updated>2021-05-20T08:22:16+00:00</updated><id>https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2021/new-preprint-in-town</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2021/new-preprint-in-town/"><![CDATA[<p>After some time of hard work I’m happy to share my next preprint (in years!).<br/> Hopeful to start making this happen more often now. Here it is: <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2105.09260">Multipartite quantum correlations in a two-mode Dicke model</a>.<br/> This study has been done in partnership with my supervisor in Brazil, Gabriel Landi, and our colleague Mark Mitchison at Trinity College Dublin.</p>]]></content><author><name>Rodolfo R. Soldati</name></author><category term="phd"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After some time of hard work I’m happy to share my next preprint (in years!). Hopeful to start making this happen more often now. Here it is: Multipartite quantum correlations in a two-mode Dicke model. This study has been done in partnership with my supervisor in Brazil, Gabriel Landi, and our colleague Mark Mitchison at Trinity College Dublin.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pandemic update</title><link href="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2021/pandemic/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pandemic update"/><published>2021-04-02T13:56:57+00:00</published><updated>2021-04-02T13:56:57+00:00</updated><id>https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2021/pandemic</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2021/pandemic/"><![CDATA[<p>I would just like to give an update to the readers that this website is still very much alive!<br/> I haven’t posted much, but as you can imagine this is due to the current pandemic situation and the lack of activities undergoing, in general.<br/> As the reader can imagine, I am continuing the pursuit of my PhD, and I currently work at the University of Stuttgart, and also at the University of São Paulo, remotely.<br/> Hopefully we will have a more lively environment soon, and then I’ll post more interesting stuff.</p>]]></content><author><name>Rodolfo R. Soldati</name></author><category term="phd"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I would just like to give an update to the readers that this website is still very much alive! I haven’t posted much, but as you can imagine this is due to the current pandemic situation and the lack of activities undergoing, in general. As the reader can imagine, I am continuing the pursuit of my PhD, and I currently work at the University of Stuttgart, and also at the University of São Paulo, remotely. Hopefully we will have a more lively environment soon, and then I’ll post more interesting stuff.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Research period in Stuttgart</title><link href="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2020/stuttgart/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Research period in Stuttgart"/><published>2020-08-12T20:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-08-12T20:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2020/stuttgart</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://rodolfor-s.github.io/blog/2020/stuttgart/"><![CDATA[<p>I am happy to share that I will be spending some time in the University of Stuttgart as part of my PhD project.<br/> I will work with the group of Nonequilibrium quantum dynamics and Prof. Eric Lutz.<br/> That will be part of a joint PhD programme in partnership between the group of Prof. Gabriel Landi at USP and Stuttgart, financed by the DAAD and CNPq.</p>]]></content><author><name>Rodolfo R. Soldati</name></author><category term="phd"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I am happy to share that I will be spending some time in the University of Stuttgart as part of my PhD project. I will work with the group of Nonequilibrium quantum dynamics and Prof. Eric Lutz. That will be part of a joint PhD programme in partnership between the group of Prof. Gabriel Landi at USP and Stuttgart, financed by the DAAD and CNPq.]]></summary></entry></feed>